## Mike Schaekermann

49 Columbia St W, Unit 101 Waterloo, ON N2L 3K4 mschaeke@uwaterloo.ca +1 (647) 573-2908

https://cs.uwaterloo.ca/~mschaeke/

#### **OVERVIEW**

My research interest is at the intersection of machine learning and human-computer interaction. In particular, I look at how the power of human and machine intelligence may be combined to solve problems too hard to be tackled by computational methods alone. My work in this topic revolves around the analysis of medical time series data.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### Ph.D. Candidate

2016 - Present

University of Waterloo, ON, Canada

Computer Science

Advisors: Edith Law and Kate Larson

## Bachelor of Science in Engineering

2014

Salzburg University of Applied Sciences, Austria

Media Informatics

Thesis Supervisor: Lennart Nacke

#### Staatsexamen (equivalent to Bachelors)

2011

University of Marburg, Germany

Human Medicine

## AWARDS & HONOURS

International Masters Student Award — University of Waterloo	2016
Merit-based Scholarship — Salzburg University of Applied Sciences	2014
Merit-based Scholarship for Foreign Studies	2014
Engineering Scholarship — both Economic Chamber of Salzburg	2013
Nominee for the German National Academic Foundation	2009

## WORKING PAPER

Sequence-aware Active Learning for Sleep Stage Classification. Schaekermann, M., Pineau, J., Lim, A., Poupart, P., Nacke, L. E. & Law, E.

# POSITION PAPERS

Resolvable vs. Irresolvable Ambiguity: A New Hybrid Framework for Dealing with Uncertain Ground Truth. Schaekermann, M., Law, E., Williams, A. C., & Callaghan, W. (2016). In 1st Workshop on Human-Centered Machine Learning at SIGCHI 2016. San Jose, CA.

Repidly: A Lightweight Tool for the Collaborative Analysis of Biosignals and Gameplay Videos. Schaekermann, M., Nacke, L. E. (2016). In 1st Workshop on Lightweight GUR for Indies and Non-Profit Organizations at SIGCHI 2016. San Jose, CA.

The Big Picture: Preserving Context in the Decomposition of Complex Expert Tasks. Williams, A. C., Bradshaw, J., Schaekermann, M., Tse, T., Callaghan, W., & Law, E. (2016). In 1st Workshop on Microproductivity at SIGCHI 2016. San Jose, CA.

WORK Entrepreneur 2011 - 2015

## EXPERIENCE

SpontaneousOrder GmbH, Berlin, Germany

- Co-founder and Head of IT of a startup company dealing with browser-based designs for 3D-printing (https://stilnest.com/)
- Received USD 1 million in seed funding in 08/2014 (https://www.crunchbase.com/organization/stilnest), followed by additional funding rounds
- Led a medium-sized team of software engineers to build an international platform for 3D-printed designer accessories

## Visiting Researcher

2013 - 2014

Games and Media Entertainment Research Laboratory University of Ontario Institute of Technology, ON, Canada

#### **Tutor for Applied Mathematics**

2012 - 2013

Salzburg University of Applied Sciences, Austria

## Research Assistant at Core-Unit "BrainImaging"

2009 - 2010

University Medical Center, Marburg, Germany

## SELECTED PROJECTS

#### CrowdEEG

Framework to combine machine and human intelligence for the scalable and accurate analysis of human clinical EEG recordings. This is an active research project in the HCI CrowdLab at the University of Waterloo, Canada, led by professor Edith Law.

## 3D Simulation of the Human Endocrine System

Real-time 3D simulation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis, a part of the human neuro-endocrine system. This was done as final project for a course on "Simulation Methods in Physiology and Neurobiology" at the medical school of the University of Marburg, Germany.

#### Repidly

Collaborative web application for annotating gameplay videos, based on physiological time series data developed as part of my bachelor thesis at Salzburg University of Applied Sciences, Austria.

## Implicit Surface Modeling for 3D Printing

Web application enabling real-time customization and animation of 3D-printable objects. It makes use of implicit surfaces, raymarching and the iso-surface extraction algorithm Marching Cubes.

## TECHNOLOGY SKILLS

**Programming Languages:** C++, Java, C#, Assembler, Python.

**Web Development:** HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, Nginx, Apache, Node.js, Meteor, Django, MongoDB, PostgreSQL, MySQL, AWS, Heroku.

Machine Learning / AI: Decision Trees, kNN, Generalized Linear Models, Logistic Regression, Support Vector Machines, Gaussian Process, Neural Networks, Informed, Local & Adversarial Search, Constraint Satisfaction Problems, (Partially Observable) Markov Decision Processes, Multi-armed Bandits, Reinforcement Learning.

Game Development: Game Engine Architecture, Advanced Collision Detection.

Augmented Reality: Filters, Object Tracking, Feature Points (SIFT, SURF).

Computer Graphics: Programmable Graphics Pipeline, OpenGL/WebGL and Shader Programming with GLSL, Marching Cubes.

SERVICE & LEADERSHIP

Reviewer for Conferences: CHI PLAY (2016) Membership: Association for Computing Machinery

Involvement with Academic Institution: Advisor for incoming international students (2012), President of the students council (2013) at Salzburg University of

Applied Sciences, Austria

INTER-NATIONAL EXPERIENCE International PhD Student University of Waterloo, ON, Canada 2016 - Present

International Visiting Researcher

University of Ontario Institute of Technology, ON, Canada

2013 - 2014

Advisor for Incoming International Students Salzburg University of Applied Sciences, Austria

Saizburg University of Applied Sciences, Austria

2012

2007

International Student at Academic High School Avondale College, Auckland, New Zealand

LANGUAGE

SKILLS

 ${\bf English}$  - Full Professional Proficiency

TOEFL iBT (116/120)

German - Native Speaker

French, Italian, Japanse, Maori - Basics